Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Academic Affairs records, 1939-1997 MVC0031.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Academic Affairs records
1939-1997
1939-1986
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0031.RG
13.5 Linear Feet 25 document boxes
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection includes Mount Vernon Seminary, Junior College, and College course write ups and syllabi.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Syllabi and Administrative files.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 with classes held at her residence on F Street; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage.
The school was moved to 1100 M. Street N.W. in 1900 and was once again moved in 1917 to a campus on Nebraska Avenue. In 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus in 1942 as a part of the war effort. During the 1943 academic year, the Seminary held classes in Spring Valley by leasing neighborhood residences. After receiving "just compensation" for their Nebraska Avneue campus, the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas in 1945, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University and the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated in 1999. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains academic affairs materials from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College, including course syllabi and administrative files. The material dates from 1939-1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The student quizzes and tests in Series 2 Box 27 Folder 5 are restricted for 100 years from date of record creation. Access may be provided to individual items before the 100 years has passed if it is determined that the student is deceased.
Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Faculty; Courses and lectures; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Syllabi, 1939-1997; 1939-1986; Series 1; 12.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series include course syllabi from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1939-1997.
  Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Faculty; Courses and lectures; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Mrs. Lloyd Syllabi, 1939-1943; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Write ups of courses, 1942-1945; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miss Delano- Syllabi, 1943-1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Write ups of courses- Junior College, 1943-1945; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Write ups of courses, 1945-1947; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Write ups of courses, 1947-1950; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Write ups of courses, 1950-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Write ups of courses, 1952-1954; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Write ups of courses, 1954-1956; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Write ups of courses, 1956-1958; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Write ups of courses, 1958-1960; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Write ups of courses, 1960-1962; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Junior College Syllabi, 1962-1963; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Junior College Syllabi, 1962-1963; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Write ups of courses, 1962-1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Junior College syllabi spring semester, 1963; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Art History-Mathematics, Junior College syllabi, 1963- 1964; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Music-Spanish, Junior College syllabi, 1963-1964; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College syllabi first semester, 1964-1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College syllabi second semester, 1964-1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - English, Art History, 1964-1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Write ups of courses, 1964-1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College Syllabi First Semester, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College Syllabi First Semester, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College Syllabi Second Semester, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College Syllabi Second Semester, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Write ups of courses, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Syllabi, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Write ups of courses, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Syllabi, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Write ups of courses and forms, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Courses in Junior College being taken by Seminary students, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Art, Child Development, Economics, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - English, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - French, Government, History, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mathematics, Music, Philosophy, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Psychology, Science, Sociology, Spanish, Typing, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Anthropology, Art, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Biology, Chemistry, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Economics, French, History, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - English, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Mathematics, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Political Science, Psychology, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Speech, Typewriting, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Write ups of courses, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Art, Biology, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Chemistry, Economics, English, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Education, French, History, Math, Music, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Political Science, Psychology, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Religion, Spanish, Speech, Sociology, Typing, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Biology, Chemistry, Economics, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - English, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - English, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - French, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - History, Math, Music, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Political Science, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Psychology, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sociology, Spanish, Speech, Theater, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Art, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology, Biology, Chemistry, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - English, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - English, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - French, History, Mathematics, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Modern Drama, Music, Religion, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Political Science, Psychology, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sociology, Spanish, Speech, Typewriting, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Art, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - English, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - French, History, India, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Mathematics, Music, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Religion, Political Science, Psychology, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Sociology, Spanish, Speech/Drama, Typewriting, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Art, Biology, Communications, Economics, 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - English, 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - French, Geography, History, 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Mathematics, Music, 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Political Science, Psychology, 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Religion, Spanish, Speech, Sociology, Special Topics, Typewriting, 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Art, Biology, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Business, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Chemistry, Communications, English, Childhood Education, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - French, Geography, Mathematics, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Music, Political Science, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Art, Biology, Business, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Chemistry, Childhood Education, Communications, Economics, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - English, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Language, History, Interior Design, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Mathematicsm, Music, Physical Education, Political Science, Sociology, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Art, Biology, Business, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Childhood Education, Economics, English, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Foreign Language, History, Interior Design, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Mathematics, Music, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Philosophy, Political Science, Psychology, Religion, Sociology, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Art, Biology, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Childhood Education, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Communications, Economics, English, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Foreign Language, History, Interior Design, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Mathematics, Music, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Physical Education, Political Science, Religion, Sociology, Psychology, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Art, Biology, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Business Administration, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Childhood Education, Communications, Economics, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - English, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - French, History, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Interior Design, Mathematics, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Music, Political Science, Psychology, Religion, Sociology, Spanish, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Advertising, Art History, Art-Studio, Anthropology, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Biology, Business Administration, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Childhood Education, Communications, Economics, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - English, French, History, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Interior Design, Mathematics, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Political Science, Music, Psychology, Physical Education, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Religion, Sociology, Spanish, 1979-1980; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Art History, Arts and Humanities, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Art-Studio, Anthropology, Biology, Business Administration, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Childhood Education, Communications, Economics, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - English, French, History, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Human Development, Interior Design, Mathematics, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Music, Philosophy, Photography, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Political Science, Psychology, Public Affairs, Spanish, 1980-1981; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology, Art History, Studio Art, Arts and Humanities, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Biology, Business Administration, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Communications, Economics, English, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Music, Political Science, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Psychology, Public Affairs and Government, Religion, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Spanish, French, Freshmen Seminar, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Freshmen Seminar, Childhood Development, History, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Interior Design, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Mathematics, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Anthropology, Art History, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Arts and Humanities, Biology, Business Administration, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Communications, Computer Science, Economics, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - English, French, Freshmen Seminar, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Human Development, Interior Design, Mathematics, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Music, Photography, Psychology, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Public Affairs and Government, Physical Education, Religion, Spanish, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Studio Art, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Anthropology, Arts and Humanities, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Art History, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Business, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Childhood Education, Communications, Computer Science, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Economics, English, French, Freshmen Seminar, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - History, Human Development, Interior Design, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Mathematics, Music, Philosophy, Photography, Physical Education, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Political Science, Psychology, Public Affairs and Government, Skills, Spanish, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Art History, Arts and Humanities, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Studio Arts, Biology, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Business Administration, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Chemistry, Communications, Childhood Education, Computer Science, Economics, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - English, Freshmen Seminar, History, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Interior Design, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Human Development, Mathematics, Music, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy, Psychology, Physical Education, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Political Science, Religion, Spanish, Sociology, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology, Studio Arts, Art History, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Biology, Business, Communications, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Economics, English, French, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Human Development, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Interior Design, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Mathematics, Physical Education, Philosophy, Psychology, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Political Science, Religion, Spanish, Special Studies, Theater, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Graphic Communications I, 1988; Series 1 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Core 101 and 102, 1996-1997; Series 1 (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Administrative Files, 1954-1997; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet
  Arranged alphabetically.
  The materials of this series include academic affairs files from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. The files include Middle States self-studies, quizzes and exams, activity write ups, individual faculty members' files, etc. They range in date from 1939-1997.
  Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Faculty; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
  - Bobby Kilberg memos, 1975; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Course schedules, 1968-1978; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - English/Dialect materials, undated; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Jim Gray (VP Academic Affairs) files, 1997; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Educational technology, 1968; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Library book lists, 1966-1970; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Middle States study, 1986; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Middle States studies, 1958; Series 2 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Middle States study, 1958; Series 2 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Middle States studies, 1968-1976; Series 2 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Academic Affairs files, 1968-1984; Series 2 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College Seminars I and IV, 1969; Series 2 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Quizzes/exams, 1967-1971; Series 2 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The student quizzes and tests in this folder are restricted for 100 years from date of record creation. Access may be provided to individual items before the 100 years has passed if it is determined that the student is deceased.
  - Write ups of activities, 1954-1956; Series 2 (Box 27, Folder 6)